<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
    <front>
        <title-group>
            <article-title>The Influence of Fisher Knowledge on the Susceptibility of Reef Fish Aggregations to Fishing</article-title>
        </title-group>
        <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
                <name>
                    <surname>Robinson</surname>
                    <given-names>Jan</given-names>
                </name>
                <xref ref-type="aff" rid="unique"/>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
                <name>
                    <surname>Cinner</surname>
                    <given-names>Joshua E.</given-names>
                </name>
                <xref ref-type="aff" rid="unique"/>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
                <name>
                    <surname>Graham</surname>
                    <given-names>Nicholas A. J.</given-names>
                </name>
                <xref ref-type="aff" rid="unique"/>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="unique">
                <institution>ARC Center of Excellence for Coral Reef Studies, James Cook University, Townsville, Queensland, Australia</institution>
            </aff>
            <aff id="unique">
                <institution>ARC Center of Excellence for Coral Reef Studies, James Cook University, Townsville, Queensland, Australia</institution>
            </aff>
            <aff id="unique">
                <institution>ARC Center of Excellence for Coral Reef Studies, James Cook University, Townsville, Queensland, Australia</institution>
            </aff>
        </contrib-group>
        <abstract>
            <p>
                <p>Reef fishes that exhibit predictable aggregating behaviour are often considered vulnerable to overexploitation. However, fisher knowledge of this behaviour is often heterogeneous and, coupled with socioeconomic factors that constrain demand for or access to aggregated fish, will influence susceptibility to fishing. At two case study locations in Papua New Guinea, Ahus and Karkar islands, we conducted interview-based surveys to examine how local context influenced heterogeneity in knowledge of fish aggregations. We then explored the role of fisher knowledge in conferring susceptibility to fishing relative to socioeconomic drivers of fishing effort. Local heterogeneity in knowledge of aggregating behaviour differed between our case studies. At Ahus, variable access rights among fishers and genders to the main habitats were sources of heterogeneity in knowledge. By contrast, knowledge was more homogenous at Karkar and the sole source of variation was gear type. Differences between locations in the susceptibility of aggregations to fishing depended primarily on socioeconomic drivers of fishing effort rather than catchability. While Ahus fishers were knowledgeable of fish aggregations and used more selective gears, Karkar fishers were less constrained by tenure in their access to aggregation habitat. However, fishing effort was greater at Ahus and likely related to high dependency on fishing, greater access to provincial capital markets than Karkar and a weakening of customary management. Moreover, highly efficient fishing techniques have emerged at Ahus to exploit the non-reproductive aggregating behaviour of target species. Understanding how knowledge is structured within fishing communities and its relation to socioeconomic drivers of fishing effort is important if customary practices for conservation, such as 
                    <italic>tambu</italic> areas, are to be supported. The findings of this study call for a holistic approach to assessing the risks posed to reef fish aggregations by fishing, grounded in the principals of fisheries science and emerging social-ecological thinking.
                </p>
            </p>
        </abstract>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec>
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The depletion of reef fish biomass is often attributed to overfishing driven by socioeconomic drivers such as local human population density and distance from reefs to markets 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Mora1" ref-type="bibr">Mora et al., 2011</xref>–
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Cinner1" ref-type="bibr">Cinner et al., 2013</xref>. As changes to these key socioeconomic drivers increase demand for resources, reef fishes with slow life histories, such as groupers (Serranidae), are typically the first to be depleted 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-SadovydeMitcheson1" ref-type="bibr">Sadovy de Mitcheson et al., 2013</xref>. However, the rate of depletion will also be influenced by the ability of fishers to locate and exploit fish populations when they are most vulnerable to fishing. Vulnerability to fishing increases when fish aggregate or school and the history of fishing is marked by developments based on exploiting this aspect of fish behaviour 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Parrish1" ref-type="bibr">Parrish, 1999</xref>–
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Pitcher1" ref-type="bibr"/>. In the context of coral reefs, the development of aggregation-based fisheries depends on many factors including local knowledge relating to fish behaviour 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Hamilton1" ref-type="bibr"/>–
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Aswani1" ref-type="bibr">Aswaniand Vaccaro, 2008</xref>, the technologies available to fishers 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Claro1" ref-type="bibr">Claro et al., 2009</xref>–
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Hamilton2" ref-type="bibr">Hamilton et al., 2011</xref> and access to aggregation sites 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-MatosCaraballo1" ref-type="bibr">Matos-Caraballo et al., 2006</xref>–
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Robinson1" ref-type="bibr">Robinson et al., 2008</xref>. It is important to understand the key ecological and socioeconomic drivers controlling the evolution of fisheries for aggregating species if they are to be effectively managed.
            </p>
            <p>The exploitation of reef fish spawning aggregations is an obvious example of fishers utilising knowledge on fish behaviour to target populations when their density has increased. A large number of important food fishes on coral reefs aggregate periodically at high density to spawn 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Domeier1" ref-type="bibr">Domeierand Colin, 1997</xref>–
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-SadovydeMitcheson2" ref-type="bibr">Sadovy de Mitcheson et al., 2008</xref>. Spawning aggregations represent attractive fishing opportunities since increases in density typically lead to greater catch-per-unit-effort (CPUE) 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Wilberg1" ref-type="bibr">Wilberg et al., 2010</xref> and because they are highly predictable in time and space, as evidenced by acoustic telemetry techniques that reveal spawner fidelity to specific sites and lunar periods 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Rhodes1" ref-type="bibr">Rhodes et al., 2012</xref>–
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Bijoux1" ref-type="bibr">Bijoux et al., 2013</xref>. Predictable aggregating behaviour is not, however, confined to reproduction since reef fishes also aggregate at specific times and locations for other functions, such as foraging, resting and shelter 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Meyer1" ref-type="bibr">Meyerand Holland, 2005</xref>–
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Hitt1" ref-type="bibr">Hitt et al., 2011</xref>. Fishers regularly target non-reproductive aggregations 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Parrish1" ref-type="bibr">Parrish, 1999</xref>, 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Johannes1" ref-type="bibr">Johannesand Hviding, 2000</xref>, though their vulnerability to fishing has received much less research attention than spawning aggregations.
            </p>
            <p>Regardless of their biological predictability, fisher knowledge of aggregations is heterogeneous and will influence the extent to which aggregations are perceived as predictable and exploited by fishers. Fisher knowledge maybe stratified by factors such as gender, age, location and cultural background 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Hamilton1" ref-type="bibr"/>, 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-SadovydeMitcheson2" ref-type="bibr">Sadovy de Mitcheson et al., 2008</xref>, 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Christie1" ref-type="bibr">Christieand White, 1997</xref>. For example, Hamilton et al. (2004) 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Hamilton1" ref-type="bibr"/> documented how fisher knowledge of spawning aggregations varied by clan both within and between locations in Manus Province, Papua New Guinea. Even if aggregations are predictable and their timing and location are known to fishers, accessibility to sites may be low due to factors such as prevailing weather and remoteness 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-MatosCaraballo1" ref-type="bibr">Matos-Caraballo et al., 2006</xref>–
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Robinson1" ref-type="bibr">Robinson et al., 2008</xref>, while inefficient gear use may constrain exploitation rates 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-AguilarPerera1" ref-type="bibr">Aguilar-Perera, 2006</xref>. Gender preferences and customary marine tenure that specifies ownership rights among kinship groups may also influence fisher access to fish resources 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Aswani1" ref-type="bibr">Aswaniand Vaccaro, 2008</xref>, 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Cinner2" ref-type="bibr">Cinner, 2007</xref>. Furthermore, fishing effort on aggregations may be constrained by limited market access or fish preservation capacity 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-MatosCaraballo1" ref-type="bibr">Matos-Caraballo et al., 2006</xref>. Consequently, the vulnerability to fishing conferred by aggregation formation will depend on both fisher knowledge of aggregating behaviour and socioeconomic drivers influencing aggregation exploitation.
            </p>
            <p>Fisher knowledge of fish aggregating behaviour will be influenced by cognitive processes (such as recall) and the formation of heuristic models 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Daw1" ref-type="bibr">Daw et al., 2011</xref>. To understand how such knowledge develops, it is informative to deconstruct the biological attributes of this behaviour and consider their effects on fisher memory. The biological attributes of aggregation behaviour can be categorised by their temporal, spatial and physical manifestations. Firstly, aggregation formation aligning with diurnal, lunar and seasonal periods is likely to promote recall since coral reef fishers often allocate effort according to such schedules 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Aswani2" ref-type="bibr">Aswani, 1998</xref>. Secondly, reef fishers often have detailed knowledge on the broad-scale (i.e. seascape) distribution of resources 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Aswani1" ref-type="bibr">Aswaniand Vaccaro, 2008</xref>, which coincides with the fact that aggregations often form at prominent reef features 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Connell1" ref-type="bibr">Connelland Kingsford, 1998</xref>–
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Choat1" ref-type="bibr"/>. However, some species are more mobile and therefore less predictable in space than others when aggregated for spawning (e.g. Carangidae) 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Heyman1" ref-type="bibr">Heymanand Kjerfve, 2008</xref>. Lastly, the size of aggregations formed is expected to influence recall since memory varies according to how pleasurable, unusual or emotive an experience is 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Matlin1" ref-type="bibr"/>, while the presence of eggs or milt (i.e. spawning) are physical manifestations of behaviour that enable fishers to reconcile aggregation formation with biological function. In combination, these attributes are expected to influence the extent to which fishers develop knowledge on aggregations and perceive them as predictable.
            </p>
            <p>Assessing the status of aggregating reef fish populations is problematic due to the data-poor context of their fisheries 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Sadovy1" ref-type="bibr">Sadovyand Domeier, 2005</xref>. Vulnerability assessment frameworks developed for data-poor contexts, which combine measures of a species productivity and susceptibility to a fishery, (e.g. 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Hobday1" ref-type="bibr">Hobday et al., 2011</xref>–
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Patrick1" ref-type="bibr">Patrick et al., 2010</xref>), are therefore worth examining for such species. Productivity defines the capacity of a stock to recover rapidly following depletion, while susceptibility is the potential for the stock to be impacted by the fishery 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Patrick1" ref-type="bibr">Patrick et al., 2010</xref>. Measures of productivity are generally available for reef fishes through empirical tools based on life history invariants 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Froese1" ref-type="bibr"/>, whereas indicators of susceptibility can be tailored to the specific fisheries being assessed in terms of patterns in catchability and socioeconomic drivers 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Patrick1" ref-type="bibr">Patrick et al., 2010</xref>. Thus, a population's susceptibility to aggregation fishing will be governed by catchability that, among other factors, relates to the accessibility of the aggregation site and the selectivity or efficiency of gears used at the site 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-ArregunSnchez1" ref-type="bibr">Arreguín-Sánchez, 1996</xref>. Catchability will in turn be driven by socioeconomic drivers, such as market access and dependency on fishing, that influence technological development and fishing effort 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Cinner1" ref-type="bibr">Cinner et al., 2013</xref>, 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Cinner3" ref-type="bibr">Cinner et al., 2009</xref>. However, aggregations are often transient phenomena, particularly in the case of spawning aggregations 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Domeier1" ref-type="bibr">Domeierand Colin, 1997</xref>, and fisher knowledge of their dynamics should be considered a critical component of susceptibility to fishing. Fisher knowledge will effectively act as the basis for the development of an aggregation-based fishery, the trajectory of which is subsequently affected by catchability attributes and socioeconomic drivers.
            </p>
            <p>Studies documenting fisher knowledge of reef fish aggregations have primarily gathered information in order to identify research, conservation and management priorities 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Samoilys1" ref-type="bibr">Samoilys et al., 2006</xref>. Attempts to quantify the influence of fisher knowledge in the susceptibility of populations to aggregation fishing are lacking, as is the use of indicator-based vulnerability frameworks for these fisheries. In this study, we aimed to examine how fisher knowledge of reproductive and non-reproductive aggregations influences the susceptibility of populations to fishing at two case study sites in Papua New Guinea. The specific research questions were: (1) to what extent are fishers knowledgeable of aggregations and do they perceive them as predictable?; (2) how does variation in fisher knowledge of aggregations relate to local socioeconomic indicators?, and (3), what is the influence of fisher knowledge in conferring susceptibility to fishing relative to catchability and socioeconomic drivers of fishing pressure.
            </p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
            <title>Materials and Methods</title>
        </sec>
        <sec>
            <title>Ethics statement</title>
            <p>The study was approved by the Human Ethics Research Committee of James Cook University (Ethics Approval Number H4812). A permit was obtained for research in Papua New Guinea (Permit number 10350012505). Due to low levels of literacy at our study locations, the Human Ethics Research Committee approved for fishers to provide verbal consent to participate in the study, according to the following procedures. An information sheet detailing the aims of the research and how data were to be used was translated verbally to participants, which also specified their rights to withdraw their information at any time and guaranteed their anonymity as participants. This was followed by verbally translating a consent form to participants. Upon consent, the consent form was signed by the lead author (JR) and translator, copies of which are stored with the unprocessed data at James Cook University. For follow-on contact with the lead author, copies of the information sheet were left with clan leaders at each location.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
            <title>Study locations and communities</title>
            <p>We studied reef fisheries at two locations in Papua New Guinea, representing two extremes of fishing pressure and comprising gear and fishing practices common to the region 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Cinner2" ref-type="bibr">Cinner, 2007</xref>. Studies focused on the communities of Ahus Island (Manus Province) and Muluk and Wadau villages, Karkar Island (Madang Province) (
                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#pone-0091296-g001">Figure 1</ext-link>). Karkar is a large, elevated (1,839 m) volcanic island and fishing is a secondary occupation to agriculture. By contrast, fishing is the primary occupation for the community on the small (28 ha), low-lying Ahus Island where terrestrial resources are limited 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Cinner2" ref-type="bibr">Cinner, 2007</xref>. The two locations also differ in coastal geomorphology and habitats. Fishers from Karkar have access to a narrow (&lt;1 km) fringing reef system of less than 150 ha with a narrow lagoon 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Cinner2" ref-type="bibr">Cinner, 2007</xref>, 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Feary1" ref-type="bibr">Feary et al., 2010</xref>, whereas fishers at Ahus Island are surrounded by a wide (&gt;4 km in the west), extensive lagoon system of approximately 550 ha 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Cinner2" ref-type="bibr">Cinner, 2007</xref>.
            </p>
            <fig>
                <label>Figure 1</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>Study locations.</title>
                    <p>Papua New Guinea with details (insets) of Ahus Island, Manus Province, and Karkar Island, Madang Province.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="g001.png" xlink:type="simple" mimetype="image"/>
            </fig>
            <p>Fishers at the study sites use a combination of gear types including line, net and spears. Fishing effort at Ahus primarily comprises use of lines and spearguns (97%, of total fishing effort), whereas effort at Karkar comprises both of these gears (72%) in combination with hand spearing (24%). By comparison, a small proportion (&lt;4%) of fishing effort at both study sites involves use of nets 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Cinner2" ref-type="bibr">Cinner, 2007</xref>. Resource use is governed by a system of customary marine tenure (CMT) that recognises local ownership of inshore marine resources. Tenure in Karkar is a relatively centralised approach where governance is controlled by a council of chiefs. There is relatively high mobility, with fishers having the ability to switch between gears and fishing grounds 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Cinner2" ref-type="bibr">Cinner, 2007</xref>. By contrast, tenure at Ahus is highly decentralized and access to fishing grounds and gears (particularly nets) is controlled by kinship group (individuals, families, clans). Both study communities have traditionally used customary taboos (
                <italic>tambu</italic>) to restrict fishing in certain areas in an effort to influence catchability (i.e. make fish less wary of spear fishers) or rebuild biomass for feasts 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Feary1" ref-type="bibr">Feary et al., 2010</xref>–
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Cinner4" ref-type="bibr">Cinner et al., 2005</xref>.
            </p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
            <title>Quantifying fisher knowledge of aggregating behaviour and predictability</title>
            <p>Interviews were conducted with fishers at Ahus (n = 16) and Karkar (Muluk: n = 7; Wadau: n = 9) in October 2012 to quantify fisher knowledge on aggregating behaviour and to develop an index of knowledge pertaining to fisher perceptions of aggregation predictability. At Karkar, interviews were conducted with all fishers for whom fishing was a regular livelihood activity. In Ahus, where the proportion of residents engaged in fishing was high by comparison, a sample of fishers, representative of fisher gender, clan membership and gear use, was taken. After pilot studies (n = 4) with Karkar fishers, a semi-structured questionnaire was designed to investigate fisher knowledge of the form, function and predictability of aggregating behaviour for six species of reef fish common to fisheries in both locations. The six species comprised two groupers (
                <italic>Epinephelus fuscoguttatus</italic>, 
                <italic>Plectropomus areolatus</italic>), two emperors (Lethrinidae; 
                <italic>Lethrinus harak</italic>, 
                <italic>L. lentjan</italic>) and two snappers (Lutjanidae; 
                <italic>Lutjanus fulviflamma</italic>, 
                <italic>L. gibbus</italic>). All species are high tropic level predators (trophic levels 3.6–4.5) and were selected to contrast forms and functions of aggregating behaviour (
                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#pone-0091296-t001">Table 1</ext-link>).
            </p>
            <table-wrap id="pone-0091296-t001">
                <label>Table 1.</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>Evidence on aggregating behaviour of study species.</title>
                </caption>
                <table>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <tr>Species</tr>
                            <tr>Aggregating behaviour</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr>
                                <italic>Epinephelus fuscoguttatus</italic>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>Primarily solitary and territorial; form large aggregations for spawning
                                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#nt101">a</ext-link>
                                <sup>, </sup>
                                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#nt102">b</ext-link>
                                <sup>, </sup>
                                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#nt103">c</ext-link>
                                <sup>, </sup>
                                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#nt104">d</ext-link>
                            </tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr>
                                <italic>Plectropomus areolatus</italic>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>Primarily solitary and territorial; form large aggregations for spawning
                                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#nt101">a</ext-link>
                                <sup>, </sup>
                                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#nt102">b</ext-link>
                                <sup>, </sup>
                                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#nt103">c</ext-link>
                                <sup>, </sup>
                                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#nt105">e</ext-link>
                            </tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr>
                                <italic>Lutjanus gibbus</italic>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>Primarily schooling; forms large aggregations for spawning
                                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#nt101">a</ext-link>
                                <sup>, </sup>
                                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#nt102">b</ext-link>
                                <sup>, </sup>
                                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#nt103">c</ext-link>
                            </tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr>
                                <italic>Lutjanus fulviflamma</italic>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>Primarily schooling; spawning aggregation formation not verified
                                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#nt101">a</ext-link>
                                <sup>, </sup>
                                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#nt103">c</ext-link>
                                <sup>, </sup>
                                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#nt106">f</ext-link>
                            </tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr>
                                <italic>Lethrinus lentjan</italic>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>Primarily solitary as adults; spawning aggregation formation suspected but not verified
                                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#nt101">a</ext-link>
                                <sup>, </sup>
                                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#nt102">b</ext-link>
                                <sup>, </sup>
                                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#nt103">c</ext-link>
                                <sup>, </sup>
                                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#nt107">g</ext-link>
                            </tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr>
                                <italic>Lethrinus harak</italic>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>Primarily solitary or forms small groups (&lt;10 fish); spawning aggregation formation suspected but not verified
                                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#nt107">g</ext-link>
                                <sup>, </sup>
                                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#nt108">h</ext-link>
                            </tr>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </table-wrap>
            <p>Firstly, species recognition by fishers was established using a combination of pictures (landed specimens) and local names specific to location. Secondly, we asked fishers whether they caught each species frequently, infrequently or not at all and, if they encountered the species, to estimate the ‘poor’, ‘normal’ and ‘good’ catch rates (fish.trip
                <sup>−1</sup>) that they typically obtain for each species when using their primary gear. Thirdly, fishers were questioned on their knowledge of aggregating behaviour, initially focusing on whether they observe a species to display solitary, shoaling (groups of three or more fish displaying unsynchronised swimming) and schooling (groups of three or more fish displaying synchronised swimming) behaviour 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Pitcher1" ref-type="bibr"/>. Fishers could assign multiple behavioural types to each species, giving eight potential categories including a ‘don't know’ response. For example, a species could be identified as solitary and shoaling, or as displaying all three behaviour types. Unless specified, ‘aggregation’ refers to all forms (i.e. shoaling, schooling) and functions (e.g. resting) of social group behaviour.
            </p>
            <p>Seven attributes of the spatial, temporal and physical manifestations of aggregating behaviour were employed to quantify fisher knowledge of aggregations and their perceived predictability (
                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#pone-0091296-t002">Table 2</ext-link>). Aggregation attributes were discussed for each species and scored according to fisher responses. For some statistical tests and analyses (
                <italic>see below</italic>), an index of fisher knowledge of aggregating behaviour was calculated for each fisher and species by summing the scores for the seven aggregation attributes (maximum score = 17; 
                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#pone-0091296-t002">Table 2</ext-link>). Thus, the fisher knowledge index essentially aims to measure the predictability of aggregations as perceived by fishers. For example, to obtain a maximum score, a fisher would need to recognise that aggregations form consistently at specific locations within a small home range, that formation aligns with diel, lunar and seasonal schedules, that aggregations are large (&gt;500 fish), and that they form for spawning (
                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#pone-0091296-t002">Table 2</ext-link>). Aggregation size and spawning (presence of eggs or milt) are physical manifestations of behaviour that were assumed to promote recall and therefore perceived predictability. Since some species were reported as constantly shoaling or schooling, questions on periodicities of aggregation formation were obviously irrelevant. Therefore, fishers were asked as to whether aggregation size in frequently shoaling or schooling species (e.g. 
                <italic>L. gibbus</italic>) increased with spawning.
            </p>
            <table-wrap id="pone-0091296-t002">
                <label>Table 2.</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>Scoring of aggregation attributes based on fisher knowledge of aggregating behaviour.</title>
                </caption>
                <table>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <tr>Attribute</tr>
                            <tr>Scoring
                                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#nt109">a</ext-link>
                            </tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr>Aggregation size</tr>
                            <tr>1 = solitary or pairing</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr/>
                            <tr>2 = aggregations of 3–10 fish</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr/>
                            <tr>3 = aggregations of 10–100 fish</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr/>
                            <tr>4 = aggregations of 100–500 fish</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr/>
                            <tr>5 = aggregations larger than 500 fish</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr>Aggregation location</tr>
                            <tr>1 = aggregation location is unknown or variable</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr/>
                            <tr>2 = aggregations form in specific areas of the reef</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr>Home range</tr>
                            <tr>1 = species of high mobility and occupying large home range</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr/>
                            <tr>2 = species of low mobility and occupying small home range</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr>Spawning</tr>
                            <tr>1 = aggregation formation not associated with spawning (eggs/milt absent)</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr/>
                            <tr>2 = aggregation formation associated with spawning (eggs/milt present)</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr>Diel</tr>
                            <tr>1 = aggregation formation not aligned with time of day</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr/>
                            <tr>2 = aggregation formation aligned with particular time of day</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr>Lunar</tr>
                            <tr>1 = aggregation formation not aligned with lunar phase</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr/>
                            <tr>2 = aggregation formation aligned with particular lunar phase</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr>Seasonal</tr>
                            <tr>1 = aggregation formation not aligned with month or season</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr/>
                            <tr>2 = aggregation formation aligned with particular month or season</tr>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </table-wrap>
        </sec>
        <sec>
            <title>Socioeconomic indicators related to heterogeneity in fisher knowledge within study locations</title>
            <p>To investigate sources of variation in fisher knowledge within case study locations, data relating to socioeconomic indicators were collected during interviews. Indicators were selected based on literature pertaining to sources of variation in knowledge among coral reef fishers and included gender, dependency on fishing as a livelihood, and access rights to major reef habitats and gear types (
                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#pone-0091296-t003">Table 3</ext-link>). Gender and the main reef habitats for which fishers hold access rights often structure fisher knowledge of fish behaviour 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Hamilton1" ref-type="bibr"/>–
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Aswani1" ref-type="bibr">Aswaniand Vaccaro, 2008</xref>, 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Christie1" ref-type="bibr">Christieand White, 1997</xref>. Fishing gears vary in species selectivity and the habitats where they can be deployed, influencing the potential for fishers to capture and develop knowledge of species behaviour 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Crona1" ref-type="bibr">Crona, 2006</xref>. Finally, dependency on fishing influences levels of fisher knowledge 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Davis1" ref-type="bibr">Davisand Wagner, 2003</xref> and was derived from fisher rankings of the importance of fishing as a livelihood (primary, secondary, tertiary) (
                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#pone-0091296-t003">Table 3</ext-link>).
            </p>
            <table-wrap id="pone-0091296-t003">
                <label>Table 3.</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>Socioeconomic indicators used in redundancy analysis (RDA) to identify sources of variation in fisher knowledge of aggregating behaviour.</title>
                </caption>
                <table>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <tr>Factor</tr>
                            <tr>Measurement level or category</tr>
                            <tr>Ahus</tr>
                            <tr>Karkar</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr>Fisher gender</tr>
                            <tr>Male</tr>
                            <tr>12</tr>
                            <tr>15</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr/>
                            <tr>Female</tr>
                            <tr>4</tr>
                            <tr>1</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr>Fisher access to habitat</tr>
                            <tr>Lagoon only</tr>
                            <tr>5</tr>
                            <tr>0</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr/>
                            <tr>Outer reefs only</tr>
                            <tr>4</tr>
                            <tr>0</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr/>
                            <tr>All habitats</tr>
                            <tr>7</tr>
                            <tr>16</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr>Primary gear type</tr>
                            <tr>Line</tr>
                            <tr>9</tr>
                            <tr>13</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr/>
                            <tr>Speargun</tr>
                            <tr>6</tr>
                            <tr>2</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr/>
                            <tr>Net</tr>
                            <tr>1</tr>
                            <tr>1</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr>Dependency on fishing</tr>
                            <tr>Primary</tr>
                            <tr>13</tr>
                            <tr>2</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr/>
                            <tr>Secondary</tr>
                            <tr>2</tr>
                            <tr>7</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr/>
                            <tr>Tertiary</tr>
                            <tr>1</tr>
                            <tr>7</tr>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </table-wrap>
        </sec>
        <sec>
            <title>Fisher knowledge and the susceptibility of aggregations to fishing</title>
            <p>A productivity-susceptibility analysis (PSA) using the bivariate framework of Hobday et al. (2011) 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Hobday1" ref-type="bibr">Hobday et al., 2011</xref> was employed to determine the relative importance of fisher knowledge in conferring susceptibility of aggregations to exploitation, and to assess the overall risk to populations posed by aggregation fishing. PSA reduces life history parameters associated with species productivity to a single x-axis index and susceptibility attributes to an index on the y-axis. In line with the approach of Hobday et al. (2011) 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Hobday1" ref-type="bibr">Hobday et al., 2011</xref>, we scored seven life history parameters (
                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#pone-0091296-t004">Table 4</ext-link>) for the six species, where productivity score categories are: 1 = high, 2 = moderate and 3 = low productivity. Parameter estimates for each species were derived using the life-history tool of Fishbase.org 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Froese1" ref-type="bibr"/>. Cut-off points dictating membership of each productivity category were adopted from those used for fisheries of the United States, which include fisheries for reef fishes analogous to those of Papua New Guinea 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Patrick1" ref-type="bibr">Patrick et al., 2010</xref>. Fecundity was subsequently omitted from the index since data were lacking for the study species.
            </p>
            <table-wrap id="pone-0091296-t004">
                <label>Table 4.</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>Attributes and their scoring system employed for productivity-susceptibility analysis (PSA).</title>
                </caption>
                <table>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <tr>Category</tr>
                            <tr>Attribute</tr>
                            <tr>Scoring</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr>Productivity</tr>
                            <tr>Average age at maturity</tr>
                            <tr>1: &lt;2 years; 2: 2–4 years; 3: &gt;4 years</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr/>
                            <tr>Average maximum age</tr>
                            <tr>1: &lt;10 years; 2: 10–30 years; 3: &gt;30 years</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr/>
                            <tr>Average size at maturity</tr>
                            <tr>1: &lt;30 cm; 2: 30–50 cm; 3: &gt;50 cm</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr/>
                            <tr>Average maximum size</tr>
                            <tr>1: &lt;60 cm; 2: 60–150 cm; 3: &gt;150 cm</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr/>
                            <tr>Reproductive strategy</tr>
                            <tr>1: broadcast spawner; 2: demersal egg layer; 3: live bearer</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr/>
                            <tr>Trophic level</tr>
                            <tr>1: &lt;2.5; 2: 2.5–3.5; 3: &gt;3.5</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr>Catchability</tr>
                            <tr>Fisher knowledge index</tr>
                            <tr>1: index scores 1–6; 2 :index scores 7–12; 3: index scores 13–17</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr/>
                            <tr>Availability</tr>
                            <tr>Proportion of fisher's effort allocated in aggregation habitat, 1: none; 2: some; 3: all</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr/>
                            <tr>Encounterability</tr>
                            <tr>Species occurrence in fisher's catch, 1: never; 2:infrequently; 3: frequently</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr/>
                            <tr>Selectivity</tr>
                            <tr>1: gears unselective for species; 2: uses one of the two most selective gears; 3: uses both of the two most selective gears</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr>Socio-economics</tr>
                            <tr>Habitat impact of gear</tr>
                            <tr>1: fisher uses spear guns and/or hook-and-line; 2: fisher uses gill nets; 3: fisher uses scare lines</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr/>
                            <tr>Fishing effort</tr>
                            <tr>1: 10–50 hrs/month; 2: 75–120 hrs/month; 3: 145–265 hrs/month</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr/>
                            <tr>Preference</tr>
                            <tr>1: low and medium preference spp.; 2: high preference spp.; 3: very high preference spp.</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr/>
                            <tr>Dependency on fishing</tr>
                            <tr>Importance of fishing as an occupation, 1: tertiary; 2: secondary; 3: primary</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr/>
                            <tr>Management strategy</tr>
                            <tr>Ownership rights and conservation measures (i.e. closures), 1: both exist; 2: one or the other exists; 3: none exist at study location</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr/>
                            <tr>Access to markets
                                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#nt112">*</ext-link>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>1: Sell/barter catch in village; 2: sell/barter catch in neighbouring villages; 3: sell/barter catch in provincial capital markets.</tr>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </table-wrap>
            <p>The four susceptibility attributes of Hobday et al. (2011) 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Hobday1" ref-type="bibr">Hobday et al., 2011</xref> were adapted to address the susceptibility of populations to aggregation fishing. Firstly, the attribute of availability primarily concerns the overlap (spatial and depth) between fishing effort and species or population distribution, or in our case the access fishers have to habitats where aggregations or schools are perceived to occur (
                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#pone-0091296-t004">Table 4</ext-link>). Secondly, the attribute of encounterability concerns the likelihood that a specific gear will encounter aggregated fish if sites are available to fishers. Fisher responses to the question on whether they catch the species frequently, infrequently or not at all were used as a measure of encounterability, assuming that the gears used by that fisher would be as efficient in catching the fish while aggregated. Thirdly, to measure selectivity, i.e. the potential of the gear to capture and retain species, we used fisher reports of catch rates (fish.trip
                <sup>−1</sup>). The mean ‘good’ catch rate across fisher responses was taken on each gear used for a species, from which gear selectivity was ranked by order of catch rate. Fourthly, we replaced post-capture mortality 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Hobday1" ref-type="bibr">Hobday et al., 2011</xref>, which is less relevant to small-scale reef fisheries where discards are minimal 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Jacquet1" ref-type="bibr">Jacquetand Pauly, 2008</xref>, with our fisher knowledge index (described above). All susceptibility attributes were scored from 1 to 3, with 1 indicative of low susceptibility and 3 of high susceptibility (
                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#pone-0091296-t004">Table 4</ext-link>).
            </p>
            <p>The attributes of Hobday et al. (2011) 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Hobday1" ref-type="bibr">Hobday et al., 2011</xref> relate to potential for a fishery to access, encounter and select for a species, i.e. catchability. However, we also wanted to quantify fishing effort (e.g. days fished each month), which in combination with catchability will determine the fishing pressure (i.e. mortality rate) on resources, and explore the socioeconomic drivers of that fishing effort. Informed by known drivers of fishing pressure in reef fisheries 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Cinner1" ref-type="bibr">Cinner et al., 2013</xref>, 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Cinner3" ref-type="bibr">Cinner et al., 2009</xref>, 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Newton1" ref-type="bibr">Newton et al., 2007</xref> and several of the ‘management attributes’ employed by Patrick et al. (2010) 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Patrick1" ref-type="bibr">Patrick et al., 2010</xref>, which also equate to socioeconomic drivers, we developed six additional susceptibility attributes. These were habitat impact of gear, fishing effort, preference for the species, dependency on fishing for a livelihood, management strategy and access to markets (
                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#pone-0091296-t004">Table 4</ext-link>). While catchability attributes were scored for each species and fisher, the socioeconomic attributes were not species-specific and combined fisher and location-level scoring (
                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#pone-0091296-t004">Table 4</ext-link>). A ranking of habitat impacts associated with gears used by fishers in our study was developed from Mangi and Roberts (2006) 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Mangi1" ref-type="bibr">Mangiand Roberts, 2006</xref> and Corpuz et al. (1985) 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Corpuz1" ref-type="bibr">Corpuz et al., 1985</xref>. Fishing effort was quantified for each fisher by questioning the hours and days they fish each day and week, respectively, which was converted to hours fished per month. Ranges associated with low, medium and high susceptibility was estimated by cluster analysis of individual effort reported by fishers. Preference, a location-level attribute used as a proxy for desirability or value of the species 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Patrick1" ref-type="bibr">Patrick et al., 2010</xref>, was derived for our six study species from a focus group held in each community. Dependency on fishing and access to markets are significant drivers of fishing pressure in many reef fisheries 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Cinner1" ref-type="bibr">Cinner et al., 2013</xref>, 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Newton1" ref-type="bibr">Newton et al., 2007</xref> and were derived from individual fisher rankings of the importance of fishing as a livelihood (
                <italic>as detailed above</italic>) and markets that they access, respectively. Management strategy was a location-level attribute adopted from Patrick et al. (2010) 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Patrick1" ref-type="bibr">Patrick et al., 2010</xref> but modified for the local context (
                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#pone-0091296-t004">Table 4</ext-link>) 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Cinner2" ref-type="bibr">Cinner, 2007</xref>.
            </p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
            <title>Data analysis</title>
            <p>The mean ‘normal’ catch rate estimated by fishers for each species was compared between locations using a 
                <italic>t</italic>-test, assuming unequal variances. For each species, associations between fisher knowledge on aggregation form at Ahus and Karkar were analysed by constructing contingency tables of the frequency of observation for each of the eight categories (solitary, shoaling, schooling, combinations of the three forms, and the ‘don't know’ response). Cramér's 
                <italic>V</italic> contingency coefficient was used as the measure of association; the coefficient ranges between 0 (no association) and 1 (perfect association). Since expected frequencies were less than five for a high proportion of cells in the contingency table, 
                <italic>p</italic>-values were calculated using Monte Carlo simulation (10,000 sampled tables).
            </p>
            <p>Several methods were employed to examine how fisher knowledge of aggregations varied by location and species. Firstly, for each species and aggregation attribute, fisher respondent scores were averaged in each location and the difference between the averages (Ahus minus Karkar) plotted. Secondly, Mann-Whitney U tests were used to compare fisher responses in each location, again for each species and attribute, with exact significance (2-sided) 
                <italic>p</italic>-values reported rather than asymptotic values due to small sample sizes (n≤17). Owing to the risk of type 1 errors arising from multiple comparisons, 
                <italic>p</italic>-values were adjusted with a false discovery rate (FDR) correction for multiple testing using the Benjamini-Hochberg method 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Benjamini1" ref-type="bibr">Benjaminiand Hochberg, 1995</xref>. To make comparisons between locations, the fisher knowledge index was averaged across fishers for each location and the same statistical method as that applied to individual aggregation attributes was used. For statistical tests of variation in both individual aggregation attributes and in the fisher knowledge index, comparisons were restricted to those fishers knowledgeable on the species and its behaviour (i.e. excluding fishers that do not catch the species).
            </p>
            <p>Redundancy analysis (RDA), which combines concepts of ordination and regression 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Legendre1" ref-type="bibr"/>, was used to examine the relationship between socioeconomic indicators (
                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#pone-0091296-t003">Table 3</ext-link>) and variance in fisher knowledge. RDA was conducted separately for each case study as the two locations differ significantly in their socioeconomic conditions and the aim was to examine local sources of variation in fisher knowledge. Here, all fisher respondents for a location were included in the analysis (n = 16) since variation in knowledge was integral to the analysis. However, results for Ahus should be treated with caution since sample size relative to the number of indicator (factor) levels imposed limitations on the RDA. Access to habitat was not included in the RDA for Karkar since it did not vary among respondents.
            </p>
            <p>Estimates of productivity attributes were averaged to give a single productivity score per species. To assess the relative importance of catchability and socioeconomic drivers of fishing pressure for the six species, each susceptibility attribute was first scored for each fisher respondent individually and then averaged across fishers to give a single attribute score for each location. Within location, the susceptibility attributes were combined by averaging across two sets of attributes; (1) the full set of 10 susceptibility attributes, and (2) the four catchability attributes (
                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#pone-0091296-t004">Table 4</ext-link>). Consequently, two bivariate PSA plots were produced for the 12 fish populations (six species per location), one for productivity and the full set of susceptibility attributes, and a second for productivity and using only the four catchability attributes (we only present the PSA plot for the full set of susceptibility attributes). From both of these PSA plots, overall vulnerability (or risk) was derived for each population at Ahus and Karkar by taking the Euclidean distance between the origin and population location in the bivariate space 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Hobday1" ref-type="bibr">Hobday et al., 2011</xref>. Wilcoxon Signed Rank tests were used to determine if overall vulnerability (with species as paired samples and location as treatments) differed between Ahus and Karkar for the full susceptibility attribute set and for the catchability attributes. Exact significance (2-sided) 
                <italic>p</italic>-values are reported due to the small number of paired-samples (n = 6).
            </p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
            <title>Results</title>
            <p>A greater proportion of females engaged in fishing at Ahus and fishers were more dependent on fishing for a livelihood than their counterparts from Karkar (
                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#pone-0091296-t003">Table 3</ext-link>). Lines were the dominant gear type in both locations but a greater proportion of fishers from Ahus used spearguns as their primary gear. Contrasting with Karkar, some fishers from Ahus reported that they were limited to fishing in the lagoon or on the outer reefs (
                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#pone-0091296-t003">Table 3</ext-link>). Based on the median response among fishers, groupers were encountered infrequently in the catches at both study locations. The four species of snapper and emperor were encountered frequently in the catches of Karkar fishers, while at Ahus 
                <italic>L. gibbus</italic> and 
                <italic>L. harak</italic> were encountered frequently and 
                <italic>L. fulviflamma</italic> and 
                <italic>L. lentjan</italic> infrequently, again based on median fisher response. Reported catch rates of snappers tended to be greater than those of emperors and groupers (
                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#pone-0091296-g002">Figure 2</ext-link>). Comparing between locations, the mean reported catch rates did not differ for most species. However, the mean catch rate for 
                <italic>E. fuscoguttatus</italic> was greater at Karkar, while the opposite was true for 
                <italic>L. gibbus</italic>.
            </p>
            <fig>
                <label>Figure 2</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>Catch rates reported by fishers for the six study species.</title>
                    <p>Data are the ‘normal’ catch rates fishers expect to obtain on a fishing trip, given as mean no. fish/trip
                        <sup>−1</sup> with standard error bars. For each species, results of 
                        <italic>t</italic>-tests comparing mean catch rates between locations are shown, with significant differences indicated by bold font.
                    </p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="g002.png" xlink:type="simple" mimetype="image"/>
            </fig>
            <p>Fishers from Ahus and Karkar had different perceptions on the forms of aggregating behaviour exhibited by the two groupers (
                <italic>E. fuscoguttatus</italic>: 
                <italic>V</italic> = 0.237, 
                <italic>p</italic> = 0.584; 
                <italic>P. areolatus</italic>: 
                <italic>V = </italic>0.393, 
                <italic>p</italic> = 0.335). The groupers were primarily perceived as solitary by fishers from Karkar while a larger proportion of Ahus fishers recognised that they are generally solitary but also form spawning aggregations (
                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#pone-0091296-g003">Figure 3a,b</ext-link>). By contrast, fishers from both Ahus and Karkar perceived snapper aggregating behaviour to be complex, alternating between solitary occurrence, loose shoal formation and synchronised schooling (
                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#pone-0091296-g003">Figure 3c,d</ext-link>). In spite of this complexity, there were significant associations between locations in how fishers perceived the forms of aggregating behaviour (
                <italic>L. gibbus</italic>: 
                <italic>V</italic> = 0.708, 
                <italic>p</italic> = 0.009; 
                <italic>L. fulviflamma</italic>: 
                <italic>V = </italic>0.674, 
                <italic>p</italic> = 0.025). Emperor aggregating behaviour was also considered more complex than that of groupers, encompassing reports of schooling by two fishers, but also tended towards solitary and shoaling behaviour (
                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#pone-0091296-g003">Figure 3e,f</ext-link>). Aggregation formation was considered a much more common behaviour by fishers on Ahus, especially for 
                <italic>L. harak</italic>. As with the two groupers, the null hypothesis of no association between locations in perceived behaviour was accepted for the lethrinids (
                <italic>L. lentjan</italic>: 
                <italic>V</italic> = 0.732, 
                <italic>p</italic> = 0.07; 
                <italic>L. harak</italic>: 
                <italic>V</italic> = 0.229, 
                <italic>p</italic> = 1.0).
            </p>
            <fig>
                <label>Figure 3</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>Fisher knowledge of the aggregating behaviour of study species.</title>
                    <p>Stacked bars represent the proportion of fishers in Ahus and Karkar identifying the six study species as exhibiting solitary (SOL), shoaling (SHO) and schooling (SCH) behaviour, or any combinations thereof (SOL-SHO, SOL-SCH, SHO-SCH). DK denotes the proportion of fishers who didn't know the aggregating behaviour of the species.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="g003.png" xlink:type="simple" mimetype="image"/>
            </fig>
            <p>Ahus fishers were generally more knowledgeable on the seasonal, lunar and diel periodicity of aggregations for 
                <italic>L. lentjan</italic>, 
                <italic>L. harak</italic> and 
                <italic>E. fuscoguttatus</italic> (
                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#pone-0091296-g004">Figure 4</ext-link>). By contrast, Ahus and Karkar fishers did not differ statistically in their knowledge of aggregation attributes for 
                <italic>L. gibbus</italic> and 
                <italic>P. areolatus</italic>, while significant differences for 
                <italic>L. fulviflamma</italic> were limited to a greater knowledge of aggregation lunar timing among Ahus fishers. Fisher knowledge of aggregation formation or increased catchability being associated with spawning was also more common on Ahus for 
                <italic>L. lentjan</italic>, 
                <italic>L. harak</italic> and 
                <italic>E. fuscoguttatus</italic>. Moreover, aggregation locations for these three species were perceived as more predictable by Ahus fishers. There were no differences between Ahus and Karkar in the perceived home range sizes of the six species and the only species for which perceptions of aggregation size differed significantly was 
                <italic>L. harak</italic>, with larger aggregations perceived on Ahus (
                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#pone-0091296-g004">Figure 4</ext-link>).
            </p>
            <fig>
                <label>Figure 4</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>Differences in fisher knowledge of aggregation attributes between study locations.</title>
                    <p>For each species and location, attribute scores were averaged among fishers. Average The results of statistical tests (Wilcoxon Signed Rank tests) comparing the vulnerability of populations (species pooled) at Ahus and Karkar are given in the panel titles.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="g004.png" xlink:type="simple" mimetype="image"/>
            </fig>
            <p>For Ahus, ordination of species by fisher knowledge of their aggregating behaviour loosely clustered 
                <italic>L. lentjan</italic>, 
                <italic>E. fuscoguttatus</italic> and 
                <italic>P. areolatus</italic>, separating them from the other species along the first canonical axis that accounted for 44.9% of the variation (
                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#pone-0091296-g005">Figure 5</ext-link>). Knowledge of the aggregating behaviour of these three species was primarily held by male fishers, whereas female and net fishers who fish in the lagoon were more knowledgeable of 
                <italic>L. harak</italic> (
                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#pone-0091296-t005">Table 5</ext-link>). Knowledge of snapper (
                <italic>L. gibbus</italic> and 
                <italic>L. fulviflamma</italic>) aggregating behaviour was largely shared among fishers, with the species orientated on the second canonical axis that only accounted for 6.1% of the variation. Therefore, with the exception of snappers, knowledge of species aggregating behaviour at Ahus was heterogeneous and explained by fisher gender and right of access to the major reef habitats (
                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#pone-0091296-t005">Table 5</ext-link>).
            </p>
            <fig>
                <label>Figure 5</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>Socioeconomic indicators associated with variation in fisher knowledge at Ahus Island.</title>
                    <p>A redundancy analysis plot of fisher knowledge relating to aggregating behaviour of six study species. Indicators are fisher gender (black circles), fisher access to lagoon, outer reef or all habitats (white triangles), primary gear type (grey squares) and primary, secondary or tertiary dependency on fishing (inverted grey triangles).</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="g005.png" xlink:type="simple" mimetype="image"/>
            </fig>
            <table-wrap id="pone-0091296-t005">
                <label>Table 5.</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>Variation in fisher knowledge of aggregating behaviour explained by socioeconomic indicators.</title>
                </caption>
                <table>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <tr/>
                            <tr>Ahus</tr>
                            <tr>Karkar</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr>Factor: factor level</tr>
                            <tr>Explains (%)</tr>
                            <tr>
                                <italic>P</italic>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>Explains (%)</tr>
                            <tr>
                                <italic>P</italic>
                            </tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr>Fisher gender: male</tr>
                            <tr>31.4</tr>
                            <tr>
                                <bold>0.004</bold>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>4.8</tr>
                            <tr>0.582</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr>Fisher gender: female</tr>
                            <tr>31.4</tr>
                            <tr>
                                <bold>0.008</bold>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>4.8</tr>
                            <tr>0.534</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr>Access to habitat: lagoon only</tr>
                            <tr>43.1</tr>
                            <tr>
                                <bold>0.002</bold>
                            </tr>
                            <tr/>
                            <tr/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr>Access to habitat: outer reefs only</tr>
                            <tr>11.6</tr>
                            <tr>0.128</tr>
                            <tr/>
                            <tr/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr>Access to habitat: all habitats</tr>
                            <tr>13.8</tr>
                            <tr>0.084</tr>
                            <tr/>
                            <tr/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr>Primary gear type: line</tr>
                            <tr>8.9</tr>
                            <tr>0.266</tr>
                            <tr>10.2</tr>
                            <tr>0.124</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr>Primary gear type: speargun</tr>
                            <tr>4.8</tr>
                            <tr>0.542</tr>
                            <tr>20.3</tr>
                            <tr>
                                <bold>0.026</bold>
                            </tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr>Primary gear type: net</tr>
                            <tr>6.7</tr>
                            <tr>0.472</tr>
                            <tr>5.2</tr>
                            <tr>0.494</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr>Dependency on fishing: primary</tr>
                            <tr>3.3</tr>
                            <tr>0.662</tr>
                            <tr>4.4</tr>
                            <tr>0.644</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr>Dependency on fishing: secondary</tr>
                            <tr>6.5</tr>
                            <tr>0.532</tr>
                            <tr>8.9</tr>
                            <tr>0.27</tr>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <tr>Dependency on fishing: tertiary</tr>
                            <tr>1.1</tr>
                            <tr>0.89</tr>
                            <tr>12.4</tr>
                            <tr>0.084</tr>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </table-wrap>
            <p>The RDA explained less of the variation in fisher knowledge at Karkar compared to Ahus, with axes one and two accounting for 25.7% and 7.5%, respectively (
                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#pone-0091296-g006">Figure 6</ext-link>). Knowledge of grouper (
                <italic>E. fuscoguttatus</italic> and 
                <italic>P. areolatus</italic>) aggregating behaviour again clustered on the first canonical axis but was restricted to only two fishers primarily using spearguns. Use of this gear constituted the only factor that significantly explained variation in knowledge (
                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#pone-0091296-t005">Table 5</ext-link>). 
                <italic>Lutjanus fulviflamma</italic> and 
                <italic>L. gibbus</italic> orientated between the axes, again due to knowledge being largely shared among fishers, while the low level of knowledge pertaining to 
                <italic>L. lentjan</italic> behaviour was not influential on the ordination. Line and net fishers with a tertiary level of dependence on fishing were knowledgeable of 
                <italic>L. harak</italic>, but these factors were not statistically significant in explaining variation in knowledge (
                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#pone-0091296-t005">Table 5</ext-link>).
            </p>
            <fig>
                <label>Figure 6</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>Socioeconomic indicators associated with variation in fisher knowledge at Karkar Island.</title>
                    <p>A redundancy analysis plot of fisher knowledge relating to aggregating behaviour of six study species. Indicators are fisher gender (black circles), primary gear type (grey squares) and primary, secondary or tertiary dependency on fishing (inverted grey triangles).</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="g006.png" xlink:type="simple" mimetype="image"/>
            </fig>
            <p>Productivity of the six species varied from less productive groupers to the more productive emperors and snappers. Three species (
                <italic>L. harak</italic>, 
                <italic>L. lentjan</italic> and 
                <italic>L. gibbus</italic>) were equal in their productivity scores (
                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#pone-0091296-g007">Figure 7</ext-link>). All four grouper populations were in the medium risk category, while most of the other populations were low risk. However, 
                <italic>L. gibbus</italic> aggregations at Ahus were assessed to be medium risk due to a high susceptibility score.
            </p>
            <fig>
                <label>Figure 7</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>Productivity-susceptibility analysis (PSA) plot.</title>
                    <p>The susceptibility axis in this plot combines all ten attributes associated with catchability and socioeconomic drivers of fishing pressure (see 
                        <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#pone-0091296-t004">Table 4</ext-link>). The contour lines divide regions of equal vulnerability to fishing, and group species of similar risk levels: i.e. low, medium and high risk (after Hobday et al. 2011).
                    </p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="g007.png" xlink:type="simple" mimetype="image"/>
            </fig>
            <p>When all attributes were included in the measure of susceptibility, vulnerability to fishing was greater at Ahus than Karkar (
                <italic>Z</italic> = −2.2; 
                <italic>p</italic> = 0.031) (
                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#pone-0091296-g008">Figure 8</ext-link>). However, when only the four catchability attributes were included in the measure of susceptibility, vulnerability to aggregation fishing did not differ significantly between locations (
                <italic>Z</italic> = −1.6; 
                <italic>p</italic> = 0.156) (
                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#pone-0091296-g008">Figure 8</ext-link>). This occurs because differences in the four catchability attributes tend to cancel each other out, such that fisher knowledge and selectivity are higher at Ahus but the reverse is true for availability and encounterability (
                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#pone-0091296-g009">Figure 9</ext-link>). With the exception of preference for the six species, the socioeconomic attributes used in the PSA scored more highly for Ahus than Karkar (
                <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="#pone-0091296-g009">Figure 9</ext-link>). The score for fishing effort was higher at Ahus since fishers at that location averaged 93 hours of fishing each month compared to 58 hours at Karkar. Dependency on fishing was also higher, with more than 80% of fishers reporting fishing as their primary livelihood compared to 12.5% at Karkar. The majority of fishers at Ahus also reported that they use scare lines for catching snappers, ensuring that habitat impacts were also comparatively high at that location. Moreover, fishers from Ahus regularly accessed markets of neighbouring villages (neighbouring islands and the northern coast of Manus) and the provincial capital, whereas fishers from Karkar generally traded locally or occasionally in neighbouring villages on Karkar. Ownership rights and customary reef closure measures still existed at Karkar, but at Ahus fishers reported during interviews that the customary closure was no longer being respected or complied with. Consequently, including attributes relating to socioeconomic drivers resulted in a greater susceptibility of aggregations to fishing at Ahus compared to Karkar.
            </p>
            <fig>
                <label>Figure 8</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>Influence of catchability and socioeconomic susceptibility attributes on the vulnerability of populations to aggregation fishing.</title>
                    <p>Vulnerability, measured as the Euclidean distance of populations to the origin in the corresponding PSA plots, is compared for all susceptibility attributes (catchability and socioeconomic drivers; left panel) and catchability (right panel) attributes only. The results of statistical tests (Wilcoxon Signed Rank tests) comparing the vulnerability of populations (species pooled) at Ahus and Karkar are given in the panel titles.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="g008.png" xlink:type="simple" mimetype="image"/>
            </fig>
            <fig>
                <label>Figure 9</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>Case study location scores for the ten susceptibility attributes.</title>
                    <p>Clockwise from top, the first four attributes relate to catchability, while the remaining six are indicators of socioeconomic drivers. Attributes were scored from 1 (low susceptibility) to 3 (high susceptibility) for each fisher respondent or, in the case of preference and management strategy, at the level of location. For attributes scored at the respondent level, the mean score (N = 16) is given.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="g009.png" xlink:type="simple" mimetype="image"/>
            </fig>
        </sec>
        <sec>
            <title>Discussion</title>
            <p>Supportive of previous research findings in Papua New Guinea 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Hamilton1" ref-type="bibr"/>, we found that fisher knowledge of aggregating behaviour varied between our two case study communities. While this finding is unsurprising in a country of such high cultural and socioeconomic diversity, our study makes a contribution by also highlighting the influence of local context in structuring knowledge within communities. Thus, the relatively high heterogeneity in knowledge at Ahus related to rights of access among fishers and genders to the main habitats of the relatively large reef system. By contrast, knowledge was more homogenous at Karkar and the sole source of variation was primary gear type. Though knowledge of aggregation location and timing are prerequisites for exploitation, factors that drive fishing effort will ultimately determine their susceptibility to fishing since knowledge, by itself, does not ensure that fishers will seek to maximize their extraction from the fishery 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Johannes2" ref-type="bibr">Johannes, 1978</xref>–
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Colding1" ref-type="bibr">Coldingand Folke, 2001</xref>. Overfishing may be related to distance to markets 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Cinner1" ref-type="bibr">Cinner et al., 2013</xref>, while the overexploitation of spawning aggregations has been attributed to the emergence of commercial markets for aggregating species 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Sadovy1" ref-type="bibr">Sadovyand Domeier, 2005</xref>. Social norms operating outside customary tenure may also constrain fishing pressure 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Colding1" ref-type="bibr">Coldingand Folke, 2001</xref>–
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Carrier1" ref-type="bibr">Carrier, 1982</xref>. However, our study objectives required a trade-off between the qualitative interviews that are required to explore social norms and quantitative approaches involving larger sample sizes that were needed for statistical inference of the factors relating to knowledge. Additional research exploring how knowledge is structured within communities will be important for assessing the role of social norms or customary management practices, such as 
                <italic>tambu</italic> areas, in regulating fishing effort.
            </p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
            <title>Factors associated with heterogeneity in fisher knowledge of aggregating behaviour</title>
            <p>Fisher knowledge of aggregating behaviour was particularly heterogeneous at Ahus. Since variation at Ahus related to gender and access to reef habitats, it appears to stem from the decentralised tenure system that specifies ownership rights to space, species, gear and the techniques for using gears among kinship groups 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Cinner2" ref-type="bibr">Cinner, 2007</xref>, 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Carrier1" ref-type="bibr">Carrier, 1982</xref>–
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Carrier2" ref-type="bibr"/>. An understanding of how knowledge is structured and maintained among kinship groups is important since the breakdown of customs and the spread of knowledge can lead to increased fishing pressure on aggregations 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Hamilton1" ref-type="bibr"/>. By contrast, marine tenure arrangements at Karkar allow for relatively higher mobility of fishers between gears and fishing grounds 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Cinner2" ref-type="bibr">Cinner, 2007</xref>. With less specialisation in specific gears or habitats, knowledge was less structured at Karkar compared to Ahus, as indicated by the relatively low amount of variation explained by the redundancy analysis. Heterogeneity in knowledge was unrelated to dependency on fishing, which at Ahus resulted from the fact that fishing was the primary livelihood for 80% of fishers, encompassing both genders and fishers with differing right of access. Though our objective was to explore local sources of variation in knowledge, dependency on fishing may explain why fishing effort was higher and fishers used more efficient gears (i.e. scare lines) at Ahus.
            </p>
            <p>Variation in fisher knowledge of aggregating behaviour differed among the three families of reef fish. Compared to emperors and groupers, knowledge of aggregations of the two snappers was greater and relatively homogenous. Snapper aggregation locations were perceived by fishers as spatially predictable and were associated with particular features of the reef, corresponding with empirical evidence for these species 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Connell1" ref-type="bibr">Connelland Kingsford, 1998</xref>, 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Newman1" ref-type="bibr">Newmanand Williams, 2001</xref>. Of our six study species, snappers generally had the highest reported catch rates, presumably since they are schooling species and are relatively abundant, often forming an important component of reef fisheries catch in many parts of Papua New Guinea and other regions 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-McClanahan1" ref-type="bibr">McClanahanand Cinner, 2008</xref>–
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Grandcourt1" ref-type="bibr">Grandcourt et al., 2006</xref>.
            </p>
            <p>Heterogeneity in fisher knowledge relating to grouper spawning aggregations was structured by access rights or gear type, depending on location. Grouper spawning aggregations mainly form on outer reef slopes and channels 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Hamilton2" ref-type="bibr">Hamilton et al., 2011</xref>, 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Robinson1" ref-type="bibr">Robinson et al., 2008</xref>, 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Claydon1" ref-type="bibr">Claydon, 2004</xref>. Since around one third of fisher respondents at Ahus, including all females and some male fishers, were limited to using nets or fishing in the large lagoon, they are therefore unlikely to have developed knowledge of this behaviour. Gear use also plays a role in knowledge acquisition 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Crona1" ref-type="bibr">Crona, 2006</xref> and fishers using spearguns at Karkar held greater knowledge of grouper spawning aggregations, possibly benefitting from the direct observation of fish behaviour that this gear affords. However, few grouper spawning aggregations may exist at Karkar since the scales of migration (approximately 10–25 km; 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Rhodes1" ref-type="bibr">Rhodes et al., 2012</xref>, 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Rhodes2" ref-type="bibr">Rhodesand Tupper, 2008</xref>) that these species are known to undertake in attending spawning aggregations are larger than the linear extent (&lt;5 km) of the reef fished 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Feary1" ref-type="bibr">Feary et al., 2010</xref>.
            </p>
            <p>As with groupers, heterogeneity in fisher knowledge of emperor behaviour also stemmed from variable rights of access among fishers. Thus, lagoon fishers at Ahus developed specialist knowledge of the behaviour of 
                <italic>L. harak</italic>, a generally solitary species common to that habitat 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Hamilton1" ref-type="bibr"/>–
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Aswani1" ref-type="bibr">Aswaniand Vaccaro, 2008</xref>, which forms spawning aggregations and small groups for non-reproductive functions 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Ebisawa1" ref-type="bibr">Ebisawa, 2006</xref>–
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Nanami1" ref-type="bibr">Nanamiand Yamada, 2009</xref>. Reports of 
                <italic>L. lentjan</italic> spawning in aggregations were also limited to Ahus fishers, and are consistent with anecdotal reports of this behaviour from other countries 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Johannes3" ref-type="bibr"/>. Contrasting with its congener, 
                <italic>L. lentjan</italic> primarily feed in deeper water 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Parrish2" ref-type="bibr"/> and heterogeneity in knowledge emerged on Ahus as the species was mainly known to male fishers who can access the outer reefs. Fishers from both locations generally perceived emperors as being relatively mobile and of lower spatial predictability than groupers or snappers, which concurs with scientific evidence 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-KaundaArara1" ref-type="bibr">Kaunda-Araraand Rose, 2004</xref>.
            </p>
            <p>Our study was a first step in quantitatively exploring the factors that influence local ecological knowledge of reef fish aggregating behaviour within communities, but was limited to a small number of socioeconomic indicators that reflect the contemporary context of the two communities. Consequently, we did not quantify important historical aspects of these communities and the role of oral histories in transferring knowledge, which may have influenced the patterns observed in our data. For example, though we pooled respondents from the two study villages of Karkar Island in our analyses, knowledge of grouper spawning aggregations was higher (by 52%, based on the sum fisher knowledge index for both grouper species) among Muluk fishers than neighbouring fishers from Wadau. Since fishers exhibit similar dependency on fishing, this finding may reflect the differing historical context of two communities, which may have settled on the coast at different times 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Cinner2" ref-type="bibr">Cinner, 2007</xref>.
            </p>
            <p>Comparing several locations in Melanesia, Hamilton et al. (2004) 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Hamilton1" ref-type="bibr"/> found that the Titan communities from southern Manus held the richest bodies of knowledge pertaining to grouper spawning aggregation sites, which had accumulated over generations. The knowledge base that supports the complex tenure systems of Ahus and neighbouring Ponam Island also extends over many generations and is likely reinforced through cultural mechanisms such as initiation rights for certain fishing practices 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Cinner4" ref-type="bibr">Cinner et al., 2005</xref>, 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Carrier1" ref-type="bibr">Carrier, 1982</xref>. Thus, knowledge of aggregating behaviour at Ahus has likely been retained through such mechanisms and is presumably limited to clans or kinship groups that can access those resources. While it would have been informative to stratify sampling of respondents by clans or kinship groups, this poses difficulties owing to the often complex relationships in communities such as Ahus 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Cinner2" ref-type="bibr">Cinner, 2007</xref>. Adding further factors in the analysis would also have required more interviews to be conducted than our resources permitted, since RDA is a constrained ordination analysis that is sensitive to the number of factors relative to sample size. Though our RDA results should be interpreted with caution, since the number of factor levels slightly exceeded the recommended number based on sample size, unconstrained analyses (i.e. principal components analysis) yielded similar relationships between fisher knowledge and socioeconomic indicators.
            </p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
            <title>Susceptibility of reef fish populations to aggregation fishing</title>
            <p>This study demonstrated the utility of PSA in examining how attributes relating to catchability and socioeconomic drivers of fishing effort influence the susceptibility of reef fish populations to aggregation fishing. Given that experts with access to scientific information have scored susceptibility indictors in previous applications of PSA 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Hobday1" ref-type="bibr">Hobday et al., 2011</xref>, 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Patrick1" ref-type="bibr">Patrick et al., 2010</xref>, our study is also novel in that information to score indicators was sourced directly from resource users. Such an approach is more applicable to the many coral reef fisheries that lack fisheries and ecological information.
            </p>
            <p>Knowledge of fish aggregating behaviour is commonly utilized by fishers to improve catchability and returns from a fishery 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Parrish1" ref-type="bibr">Parrish, 1999</xref>. It is therefore appropriate to incorporate fisher knowledge as an indicator of susceptibility to fishing in risk analyses involving aggregating species, especially as it varies among communities 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Hamilton1" ref-type="bibr"/>. At Karkar, encounterability was higher and the main reef habitats were available for access by all fishers, including the outer reef slopes that are the typical aggregation habitat of at least three of our study species (
                <italic>E. fuscoguttatus</italic>, 
                <italic>L. gibbus</italic> and 
                <italic>P. areolatus</italic>
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Claydon1" ref-type="bibr">Claydon, 2004</xref>). However, knowledge of aggregating behaviour was less well developed than on Ahus. The selectivity of gears for many species was greater on Ahus, particularly in their use of a form of muro-ami to target snappers, whereby scare lines and nets are used to corral fish into an enclosed space where they are taken by speargun. This fishing technique is highly efficient for shoaling and schooling fish such as 
                <italic>L. gibbus</italic>
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Corpuz1" ref-type="bibr">Corpuz et al., 1985</xref>, as evidenced by the higher catch rates at Ahus. Thus, after combining fisher knowledge with availability, encounterability and selectivity, study populations were assessed as equally susceptible to aggregation fishing at Ahus and Karkar using the catchability approach of Hobday et al. (2011) 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Hobday1" ref-type="bibr">Hobday et al., 2011</xref>.
            </p>
            <p>An advantage of PSA is that the susceptibility attributes included can be adapted to local contexts or issues of importance. For example, Patrick et al. (2010) 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Patrick1" ref-type="bibr">Patrick et al., 2010</xref> developed 22 susceptibility index indicators in a PSA, including attributes relating to socioeconomic drivers of fishing pressure (termed ‘management’ attributes). This proved important to our analysis since the use of catchability attributes alone did not separate study locations, whereas the inclusion of socioeconomic drivers identified a greater potential for overfishing of aggregating populations at Ahus. These drivers are known indicators of fishing pressure and resource depletion 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Cinner1" ref-type="bibr">Cinner et al., 2013</xref>, 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Cinner3" ref-type="bibr">Cinner et al., 2009</xref>. Moreover, conservation benefits provided by the 
                <italic>tambu</italic> at Ahus will have been lost with the recent breakdown in this governance system 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Cinner2" ref-type="bibr">Cinner, 2007</xref>. It is therefore beneficial to understand the socioeconomic factors that drive demand for marine resources and may lead to greater targeting of reef fish aggregations.
            </p>
            <p>PSA and other semi-quantitative approaches are, however, sensitive to the assumptions made in developing indicators 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Hobday1" ref-type="bibr">Hobday et al., 2011</xref>. A number of assumptions had to be made in our application for aggregation-based fisheries. For example, our proxy for encounterability assumed that if a species appeared in a fisher's catch, then the gears used by that fisher were equally likely to encounter the species in aggregations if conditions of availability were met. This may be justified if aggregations did not form at depths beyond those typically fished by the gear, which would presumably affect fishers using gears that are generally constrained to shallower water (i.e. spearguns and nets) than fishers using lines. Our measure of availability was coarse but necessary in a data-poor context with limited time for observations on the spatial distribution of fishing effort. The use of CPUE to estimate selectivity was also subject to uncertainty, given the numerous factors that affect this parameter, and essentially constituted a measure of gear efficiency for a species rather than selectivity 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-ArregunSnchez1" ref-type="bibr">Arreguín-Sánchez, 1996</xref>. Further development of indicator-based frameworks for aggregation-based reef fisheries may improve on our methods for estimating susceptibility to fishing.
            </p>
            <p>An additional caveat in the use of indicator-based approaches is that they can be overly reductionist in attempting to simplify complex socio-ecological systems. Consequently, PSA can be combined with more detailed social, economic or ecological research to better understand the management implications of more complex interactions that indicators fail to capture. It is ideally applied as a participatory risk assessment tool for supporting communication, promoting understanding, building consensus and prioritizing actions as part of community-based management planning. In our application of this tool, five populations were identified to be at medium risk from aggregation fishing. However, a participatory application of PSA in the two communities may have yielded different results. For example, resource users could develop their own indicators or choose to weight indicators according to their own priorities 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Patrick1" ref-type="bibr">Patrick et al., 2010</xref>. Though PSA has a strong basis in theoretical and empirical evidence 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-ArregunSnchez1" ref-type="bibr">Arreguín-Sánchez, 1996</xref>, 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Jennings1" ref-type="bibr">Jennings et al., 1998</xref>, its validity as a predictive tool requires robust assessment 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Patrick1" ref-type="bibr">Patrick et al., 2010</xref>. We were unable to validate our application of this tool since biomass estimates for the study populations are absent. However, multispecies reef fish biomass was lower at Ahus than Karkar, both at the time of the interviews (D. Feary, pers. comm.) and in 2002 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Cinner4" ref-type="bibr">Cinner et al., 2005</xref>, 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Cinner5" ref-type="bibr">Cinner et al., 2006</xref>, which is likely indicative of the higher fishing effort at Ahus 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Cinner2" ref-type="bibr">Cinner, 2007</xref> and may also reflect the status of our study populations.
            </p>
            <p>To conclude, heterogeneity in fisher knowledge relating to reef fish aggregating behaviour will be influenced by social, economic and cultural factors that are specific to the local context. Understanding how knowledge is structured within a community will be important if customary practices for conservation, such as 
                <italic>tambu</italic> areas, are to be supported by working with relevant kinship groups. While knowledge alone does not imply that fishers will maximize extraction from a fishery, shifts in socioeconomic drivers may serve to increase fishing pressure. For example, a breakdown in ownership rights and resulting spread of knowledge among kinship groups has been identified as a cause for concern in relation to pressure on spawning aggregations in PNG 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Hamilton1" ref-type="bibr"/>. At Ahus, the relatively high susceptibility of aggregations to fishing, caused by a combination of high dependency on fishing, access to larger markets and loss of the 
                <italic>tambu</italic> areas, would be exacerbated if the system of ownership rights also weakened. However, aggregations forming for purposes other than reproduction are also predictable and may be highly susceptible to fishing if efficient gears are used 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Claro1" ref-type="bibr">Claro et al., 2009</xref>. The findings of this study therefore call for a holistic approach to assessing the risks posed by fishing on reef fish aggregations, one that is grounded in the principals of fisheries science and emerging social-ecological thinking 
                <xref rid="pone-0091296-Cinner3" ref-type="bibr">Cinner et al., 2009</xref>.
            </p>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Mora1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Global human footprints on the linkage between biodiversity and ecosystem functioning in reef fishes</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Mora</surname>
                            <given-names>C</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Aburto-Oropeza</surname>
                            <given-names>O</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Ayala Bocos</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Ayotte</surname>
                            <given-names>PM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Banks</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year>
                    <issue>4</issue>
                    <source>PLoS Biol</source>
                    <volume>9</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Cinner1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Global effects of local human population density and distance to markets on the condition of coral reef fisheries</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Cinner</surname>
                            <given-names>JE</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Graham</surname>
                            <given-names>NAJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Huchery</surname>
                            <given-names>C</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>MacNeil</surname>
                            <given-names>MA</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
                    <source>Conserv Biol</source>
                    <fpage>453</fpage>
                    <lpage>458</lpage>
                    <volume>27</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-SadovydeMitcheson1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Fishing groupers towards extinction: a global assessment of threats and extinction risks in a billion dollar fishery</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Sadovy de Mitcheson</surname>
                            <given-names>Y</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Craig</surname>
                            <given-names>MT</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Bertoncini</surname>
                            <given-names>AA</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Carpenter</surname>
                            <given-names>KE</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Cheung</surname>
                            <given-names>WWL</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
                    <source>Fish Fish</source>
                    <fpage>119</fpage>
                    <lpage>136</lpage>
                    <volume>14</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Parrish1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Using behaviour and ecology to exploit schooling fishes</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Parrish</surname>
                            <given-names>JK</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="1999">1999</year>
                    <source>Environ Biol Fishes</source>
                    <fpage>157</fpage>
                    <lpage>181</lpage>
                    <volume>55</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Pitcher1">
                <element-citation/>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Hamilton1">
                <element-citation/>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Aswani1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Lagoon ecology and social strategies: habitat diversity and ethnobiology</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Aswani</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Vaccaro</surname>
                            <given-names>I</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year>
                    <source>Hum Ecol</source>
                    <fpage>325</fpage>
                    <lpage>341</lpage>
                    <volume>36</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Claro1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Historical analysis of Cuban commercial fishing effort and the effects on management interventions on important reef fishes from 1960–2005</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Claro</surname>
                            <given-names>R</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Sadovy de Mitcheson</surname>
                            <given-names>Y</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Lindeman</surname>
                            <given-names>KC</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>García-Cagide</surname>
                            <given-names>AR</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year>
                    <source>Fish Res</source>
                    <fpage>7</fpage>
                    <lpage>16</lpage>
                    <volume>99</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Hamilton2">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Community-based conservation results in the recovery of reef fish spawning aggregations in the Coral Triangle</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Hamilton</surname>
                            <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Potuku</surname>
                            <given-names>T</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Montambault</surname>
                            <given-names>JR</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year>
                    <source>Biol Conserv</source>
                    <fpage>1850</fpage>
                    <lpage>1858</lpage>
                    <volume>144</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-MatosCaraballo1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Fishery-dependent evaluation of a spawning aggregation of tiger grouper (Mycteroperca tigris) at Vieques Island, Puerto Rico</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Matos-Caraballo</surname>
                            <given-names>D</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Posada</surname>
                            <given-names>JM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Luckhurst</surname>
                            <given-names>BE</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year>
                    <source>Bull Mar Sci</source>
                    <fpage>1</fpage>
                    <lpage>16</lpage>
                    <volume>79</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Robinson1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Dynamics of camouflage (Epinephelus polyphekadion) and brown marbled grouper (E. fuscoguttatus) spawning aggregations at a remote atoll, Seychelles</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Robinson</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Aumeeruddy</surname>
                            <given-names>R</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Jörgensen</surname>
                            <given-names>TL</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Öhman</surname>
                            <given-names>MC</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year>
                    <source>Bull Mar Sci</source>
                    <fpage>415</fpage>
                    <lpage>431</lpage>
                    <volume>83</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Domeier1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Tropical reef fish spawning aggregations: defined and reviewed</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Domeier</surname>
                            <given-names>ML</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Colin</surname>
                            <given-names>PL</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="1997">1997</year>
                    <source>Bull Mar Sci</source>
                    <fpage>698</fpage>
                    <lpage>726</lpage>
                    <volume>60</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-SadovydeMitcheson2">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>A global baseline for spawning aggregations of reef fishes</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Sadovy de Mitcheson</surname>
                            <given-names>Y</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Cornish</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Domeier</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Colin</surname>
                            <given-names>PL</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Russell</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year>
                    <source>Conserv Biol</source>
                    <fpage>1233</fpage>
                    <lpage>1244</lpage>
                    <volume>22</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Wilberg1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Incorporating time-varying catchability into population dynamic stock assessment models</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Wilberg</surname>
                            <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Thorson</surname>
                            <given-names>JT</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Linton</surname>
                            <given-names>BC</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Berkson</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
                    <source>Rev Fish Sci</source>
                    <fpage>7</fpage>
                    <lpage>24</lpage>
                    <volume>18</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Rhodes1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Reproductive movement, residency and fisheries vulnerability of brown-marbled grouper, Epinephelus fuscoguttatus (Forsskål, 1775)</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Rhodes</surname>
                            <given-names>KL</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>McIlwain</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Joseph</surname>
                            <given-names>E</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Nemeth</surname>
                            <given-names>RS</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year>
                    <source>Coral Reefs</source>
                    <fpage>443</fpage>
                    <lpage>453</lpage>
                    <volume>31</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Bijoux1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Temporal dynamics, residency and site fidelity of spawning aggregations of a herbivorous tropical reef fish, Siganus sutor</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Bijoux</surname>
                            <given-names>JP</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Dagorn</surname>
                            <given-names>L</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Berke</surname>
                            <given-names>G</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Cowley</surname>
                            <given-names>PD</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Soria</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
                    <source>Mar Ecol Prog Ser</source>
                    <fpage>233</fpage>
                    <lpage>247</lpage>
                    <volume>475</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Meyer1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Movement patterns, home range size and habitat utilization of the bluespine unicornfish, Naso unicornis (Acanthuridae) in a Hawaiian marine reserve</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Meyer</surname>
                            <given-names>CG</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Holland</surname>
                            <given-names>KM</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year>
                    <source>Environ Biol Fishes</source>
                    <fpage>201</fpage>
                    <lpage>210</lpage>
                    <volume>73</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Hitt1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Tracking and mapping sun-synchronous migrations and diel space use patterns of Haemulon sciurus and Lutjanus apodus in the U.S. Virgin Islands</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Hitt</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Pittman</surname>
                            <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Brown</surname>
                            <given-names>KA</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year>
                    <source>Environ Biol Fishes</source>
                    <fpage>525</fpage>
                    <lpage>538</lpage>
                    <volume>92</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Johannes1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Traditional knowledge possessed by the fishers of Marovo Lagoon, Solomon Islands, concerning fish aggregating behaviour</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Johannes</surname>
                            <given-names>RE</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Hviding</surname>
                            <given-names>E</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2000">2000</year>
                    <source>SPC Traditional Marine Resource and Management and Knowledge Information Bulletin</source>
                    <fpage>22</fpage>
                    <lpage>29</lpage>
                    <volume>12</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Christie1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Trends in development in coastal area management in tropical countries: from central to community orientation</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Christie</surname>
                            <given-names>P</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>White</surname>
                            <given-names>AT</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="1997">1997</year>
                    <source>Coast Manage</source>
                    <fpage>155</fpage>
                    <lpage>181</lpage>
                    <volume>25</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-AguilarPerera1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Disappearance of a Nassau grouper spawning aggregation off the southern Mexican Caribbean Coast</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Aguilar-Perera</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year>
                    <source>Mar Ecol Prog Ser</source>
                    <fpage>289</fpage>
                    <lpage>296</lpage>
                    <volume>327</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Cinner2">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Designing marine reserves to reflect local socioeconomic conditions: lessons from long-enduring customary management systems</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Cinner</surname>
                            <given-names>JE</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year>
                    <source>Coral Reefs</source>
                    <fpage>1035</fpage>
                    <lpage>1045</lpage>
                    <volume>26</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Daw1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Perceptions of trends in Seychelles artisanal trap fisheries: comparing catch monitoring, underwater visual census and fishers' knowledge</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Daw</surname>
                            <given-names>TM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Robinson</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Graham</surname>
                            <given-names>NAJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year>
                    <source>Environ Conserv</source>
                    <fpage>75</fpage>
                    <lpage>88</lpage>
                    <volume>38</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Aswani2">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Patterns of marine harvest effort in south western New Georgia, Solomon Islands: resource management or optimal foraging</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Aswani</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year>
                    <source>Ocean Coast Manage</source>
                    <fpage>207</fpage>
                    <lpage>235</lpage>
                    <volume>40</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Connell1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Spatial, temporal and habitat-related variation in the abundance of large predatory fish at One Tree Reef, Australia</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Connell</surname>
                            <given-names>SD</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Kingsford</surname>
                            <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year>
                    <source>Coral Reefs</source>
                    <fpage>49</fpage>
                    <lpage>57</lpage>
                    <volume>17</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Choat1">
                <element-citation/>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Heyman1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Characterization of transient multi-species reef fish spawning aggregations at Gladden Spit, Belize</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Heyman</surname>
                            <given-names>WD</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Kjerfve</surname>
                            <given-names>B</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year>
                    <source>Bull Mar Sci</source>
                    <fpage>531</fpage>
                    <lpage>551</lpage>
                    <volume>83</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Matlin1">
                <element-citation/>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Sadovy1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Are aggregation-fisheries sustainable? Reef fish fisheries as a case study</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Sadovy</surname>
                            <given-names>Y</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Domeier</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year>
                    <source>Coral Reefs</source>
                    <fpage>254</fpage>
                    <lpage>262</lpage>
                    <volume>24</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Hobday1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Ecological risk assessment for the effects of fishing</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Hobday</surname>
                            <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Smith</surname>
                            <given-names>ADM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Stobutzki</surname>
                            <given-names>IC</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Bulman</surname>
                            <given-names>C</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Daley</surname>
                            <given-names>R</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year>
                    <source>Fish Res</source>
                    <fpage>372</fpage>
                    <lpage>384</lpage>
                    <volume>108</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Patrick1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Using productivity and susceptibility indices to assess the vulnerability of United States fish stocks to overfishing</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Patrick</surname>
                            <given-names>WS</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Spencer</surname>
                            <given-names>P</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Link</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Cope</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Fields</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
                    <source>Fish Bull</source>
                    <fpage>305</fpage>
                    <lpage>322</lpage>
                    <volume>108</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Froese1">
                <element-citation/>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-ArregunSnchez1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Catchability: a key parameter for fish stock assessment</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Arreguín-Sánchez</surname>
                            <given-names>F</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="1996">1996</year>
                    <source>Rev Fish Biol Fish</source>
                    <fpage>221</fpage>
                    <lpage>242</lpage>
                    <volume>6</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Cinner3">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Linking social and ecological systems to sustain coral reef fisheries</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Cinner</surname>
                            <given-names>JE</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>McClanahan</surname>
                            <given-names>TR</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Daw</surname>
                            <given-names>TM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Graham</surname>
                            <given-names>NAJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Maina</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year>
                    <source>Curr Biol</source>
                    <fpage>206</fpage>
                    <lpage>212</lpage>
                    <volume>19</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Samoilys1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Preliminary findings on spawning aggregations of reef fishes in East Africa</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Samoilys</surname>
                            <given-names>MA</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Church</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Kaunda-Arara</surname>
                            <given-names>B</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Kamukuru</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Jiddawi</surname>
                            <given-names>N</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year>
                    <source>Proc 10th Int Coral Reef Symp, Okinawa</source>
                    <fpage>1335</fpage>
                    <lpage>1346</lpage>
                    <volume>1</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Feary1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Effects of customary marine closures on fish behaviour, spear-fishing success, and underwater visual surveys</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Feary</surname>
                            <given-names>DA</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Cinner</surname>
                            <given-names>JE</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Graham</surname>
                            <given-names>NAJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Januchowski-Hartley</surname>
                            <given-names>FA</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
                    <source>Conserv Biol</source>
                    <fpage>341</fpage>
                    <lpage>349</lpage>
                    <volume>25</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Cinner4">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Conservation and community benefits from traditional coral reef management at Ahus Island, Papua New Guinea</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Cinner</surname>
                            <given-names>JE</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Marnane</surname>
                            <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>McClanahan</surname>
                            <given-names>TR</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year>
                    <source>Conserv Biol</source>
                    <fpage>1714</fpage>
                    <lpage>1723</lpage>
                    <volume>19</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Crona1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Supporting and enhancing development of heterogeneous ecological knowledge among resource users in a Kenyan seascape</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Crona</surname>
                            <given-names>BI</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year>
                    <source>Ecol Soc</source>
                    <fpage>32</fpage>
                    <volume>11</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Davis1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Who knows? On the importance of identifying ‘experts’ when researching local ecological knowledge</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Davis</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Wagner</surname>
                            <given-names>JR</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year>
                    <source>Hum Ecol</source>
                    <fpage>463</fpage>
                    <lpage>489</lpage>
                    <volume>31</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Jacquet1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Funding priorities: big barriers to small-scale fisheries</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Jacquet</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Pauly</surname>
                            <given-names>D</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year>
                    <source>Conserv Biol</source>
                    <fpage>832</fpage>
                    <lpage>835</lpage>
                    <volume>22</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Newton1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Current and future sustainability of island coral reef fisheries</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Newton</surname>
                            <given-names>K</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Cote</surname>
                            <given-names>IM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Pilling</surname>
                            <given-names>GM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Jennings</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Dulvy</surname>
                            <given-names>NK</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year>
                    <source>Curr Biol</source>
                    <fpage>655</fpage>
                    <lpage>658</lpage>
                    <volume>17</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Mangi1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Quantifying the environmental impacts of artisanal fishing gear on Kenya's coral reef ecosystems</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Mangi</surname>
                            <given-names>SC</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Roberts</surname>
                            <given-names>CM</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year>
                    <source>Mar Pollut Bull</source>
                    <fpage>1646</fpage>
                    <lpage>1660</lpage>
                    <volume>52</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Corpuz1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Traditional muro-ami, an effective but resource destructive coral reef fishing gear</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Corpuz</surname>
                            <given-names>VT</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Castaneda</surname>
                            <given-names>P</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Sy</surname>
                            <given-names>JC</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="1985">1985</year>
                    <source>1CLARM Quart</source>
                    <fpage>12</fpage>
                    <lpage>13</lpage>
                    <volume>8</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Benjamini1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Controlling the false discovery rate: a practical and powerful approach to multiple testing</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Benjamini</surname>
                            <given-names>Y</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Hochberg</surname>
                            <given-names>Y</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="1995">1995</year>
                    <source>J R Stat Soc Ser B</source>
                    <fpage>289</fpage>
                    <lpage>300</lpage>
                    <volume>57</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Legendre1">
                <element-citation/>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Johannes2">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Traditional marine conservation methods in Oceania and their demise</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Johannes</surname>
                            <given-names>RE</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="1978">1978</year>
                    <source>Annu Rev Ecol Syst</source>
                    <fpage>349</fpage>
                    <lpage>364</lpage>
                    <volume>9</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Colding1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Social taboos: “Invisible” systems of local resource management and biological conservation</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Colding</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Folke</surname>
                            <given-names>C</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year>
                    <source>Ecol Appl</source>
                    <fpage>584</fpage>
                    <lpage>600</lpage>
                    <volume>11</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Carrier1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Fishing practices on Ponam Island (Manus Province, Papua New Guinea)</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Carrier</surname>
                            <given-names>JG</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="1982">1982</year>
                    <source>Anthropos</source>
                    <fpage>904</fpage>
                    <lpage>915</lpage>
                    <volume>77</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Carrier2">
                <element-citation/>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Newman1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Spatial and temporal variation in assemblages of Lutjanidae, Lethrinidae and associated fish species among mid-continental shelf reefs in the central Great Barrier Reef</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Newman</surname>
                            <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Williams</surname>
                            <given-names>DMcB</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year>
                    <source>Mar Freshw Res</source>
                    <fpage>843</fpage>
                    <lpage>851</lpage>
                    <volume>52</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-McClanahan1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>A framework for adaptive gear and ecosystem-based management in the artisanal coral reef fishery of Papua New Guinea</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>McClanahan</surname>
                            <given-names>TR</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Cinner</surname>
                            <given-names>JE</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year>
                    <source>Aquatic Conservation: Mar Freshw Ecosyst</source>
                    <fpage>493</fpage>
                    <lpage>507</lpage>
                    <volume>18</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Grandcourt1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Age, growth and reproduction of the blackspot snapper, Lutjanus fulviflamma (Forsskål, 1775), in the southern Arabian Gulf</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Grandcourt</surname>
                            <given-names>EM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Zahran Al Abdessalaam</surname>
                            <given-names>TZ</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Francis</surname>
                            <given-names>F</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year>
                    <source>Fish Res</source>
                    <fpage>203</fpage>
                    <lpage>210</lpage>
                    <volume>78</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Claydon1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Spawning aggregations of coral reef fishes: characteristics, hypotheses, threats and management</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Claydon</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year>
                    <source>Oceanogr Mar Biol Ann Rev</source>
                    <fpage>265</fpage>
                    <lpage>302</lpage>
                    <volume>42</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Rhodes2">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>The vulnerability of reproductively active squaretail coralgrouper (Plectropomus areolatus) to fishing</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Rhodes</surname>
                            <given-names>KL</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Tupper</surname>
                            <given-names>MH</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year>
                    <source>Fish Bull</source>
                    <fpage>194</fpage>
                    <lpage>203</lpage>
                    <volume>106</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Ebisawa1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Reproductive and sexual characteristics in five Lethrinus species in waters off the Ryukyu Islands</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Ebisawa</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year>
                    <source>Ichthyol Res</source>
                    <fpage>269</fpage>
                    <lpage>280</lpage>
                    <volume>53</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Nanami1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Site fidelity, size, and spatial arrangement of daytime home range of thumbprint emperor Lethrinus harak (Lethrinidae)</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Nanami</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Yamada</surname>
                            <given-names>H</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year>
                    <source>Fish Sci</source>
                    <fpage>1109</fpage>
                    <lpage>1116</lpage>
                    <volume>75</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Johannes3">
                <element-citation/>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Parrish2">
                <element-citation/>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-KaundaArara1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Out-migration of tagged fishes from marine reef national parks to fisheries in coastal Kenya</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Kaunda-Arara</surname>
                            <given-names>B</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Rose</surname>
                            <given-names>GA</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year>
                    <source>Environ Biol Fishes</source>
                    <fpage>363</fpage>
                    <lpage>372</lpage>
                    <volume>70</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Jennings1">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Life history correlates of responses to fisheries exploitation</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Jennings</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Reynolds</surname>
                            <given-names>JD</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Mills</surname>
                            <given-names>SC</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year>
                    <source>Proc R Soc B</source>
                    <fpage>333</fpage>
                    <lpage>339</lpage>
                    <volume>265</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pone-0091296-Cinner5">
                <element-citation>
                    <article-title>Periodic closures as adaptive coral reef management in the Indo-Pacific</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Cinner</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Marnane</surname>
                            <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>McClanahan</surname>
                            <given-names>TR</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Almany</surname>
                            <given-names>GR</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year>
                    <source>Ecol Soc</source>
                    <fpage>31</fpage>
                    <volume>11</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>